Guide to the Herbert Aptheker Papers, 1842-1999, (bulk 1934-1994)
Department of Special Collections
- Series 2. Aptheker Articles, Manuscripts, and Notes
  - Politics in USA, 1966 (Box 94, Folder 12)
  - Royalty statements, 1966 (Box 94, Folder 13)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Review of Gajo Petrovic's Marxism in the mid-twentieth century. -- In The Worker, 1967 June 26 (Box 94, Folder 14)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Declaration of 1776 rebukes the bombers of 1967. -- In The Worker, 1967 July 2 (Box 94, Folder 15)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Ideas in our times: The Stockholm conference on Vietnam. -- In Political Affairs, 1967 Aug. (Box 94, Folder 16)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Police brutality in the United States. -- In The Worker, 1967 Aug. 6 (Box 94, Folder 17)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. New Nazis., 1967 Aug. 27 (Box 94, Folder 18)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. A note on the history. -- The Nation. -- Vol. 205, 1967 Oct. 16 (Box 94, Folder 19)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Remarks at the 50th anniversary of Lenin's decree of peace, Leningrad., 1967 Oct. 26, ams (5 p.) (Box 94, Folder 20)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Comments on the Mideast. Presented at World Council of Peace Presidential Committee meeting, Leningrad, 1967 Oct. 27, tms (2 p.) (Box 94, Folder 21)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Comments on developments in the U.S. peace movement. Presented at World Council of Peace Presidential Committee meeting, Leningrad, 1967 Oct. 27 - 29, tms (4 p.) (Box 94, Folder 22)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Slave revolts. -- In The New South Student. -- Vol. 4, no. 6, 1967 Nov., (cy 1) (Box 94, Folder 23)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Slave revolts. -- In The New South Student. -- Vol. 4, no. 6, 1967 Nov., (cy 2) (Box 94, Folder 24)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Est takoe gosudavstvo! -- In Literary Gazette (Moscow), 1967 Nov. 5 (Box 94, Folder 25)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Another anti-comunist lie exposed, 1967 Dec. 22, tms (2 p.) (Box 94, Folder 26)
    article re: the Scottsboro rape case
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Academic freedom in the United States. -- In Ethical Impact, 1967 (Box 94, Folder 27)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Ideas in our times., 1967 (Box 94, Folder 28)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Ideas in our times., 1967 (Box 94, Folder 29)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Letters to the editor, 1967 (Box 94, Folder 30)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Parterlichkeit un objektivitat: einige Bemerkungen zur marxistischen Methodologie. Halle: Martin-Luther Universitat Halle-Wittenberg Universitatsreden, 1967 (Box 94, Folder 31)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Review of Elsa V. Goveia's Slave society in the British leeward islands at the end of the Eighteenth Century. -- In New World Quarterly. -- Vol. 3, no. 3, 1967 (Box 94, Folder 32)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Stockholm parley unites world against Viet war., [ca. 1967] (Box 94, Folder 33)
  - Aptheker articles, 1967 (Box 94, Folder 34)
  - Articles & letters to the editor by Herbert Aptheker, 1967 (Box 94, Folder 35)
  - Aptheker: personal biography, [ca. 1967] (Box 94, Folder 36)
  - Anonymous. Commentary on KFH-CBS radio question and answer with Herbert Aptheker, 1967 Feb. 9 (Box 94, Folder 37)
  - Is Peaceful Coexistence Possible Conference, Hunter College, program, 1967 June 11 (Box 94, Folder 38)
    Includes notes, quotes, and clippings
  - A peace of reconciliation. The Progressive, 1967 Aug. (Box 95, Folder 1)
  - International Publisher Book News. Autobiography of W.E.B. Du Bois press release, 1967 Nov. (Box 95, Folder 2)
  - Pope Paul VI. On the development of peoples (Populorum Progresivo), 1967 - 1973 (Box 95, Folder 3)
    Includes notes by Herbert Aptheker.
  - Notes, 1967 - 1969 (Box 95, Folder 4)
  - Notes on founding of AIMS, ca. 1967 - 1968 (Box 95, Folder 5)
  - Lecture notes, 1967 (Box 95, Folder 6)
  - Aptheker personal news clippings [1 of 2], 1967 (Box 95, Folder 7)
  - Aptheker personal news clippings [2 of 2], 1967 (Box 95, Folder 8)
  - Magazine and newspaper clippings re: Herbert Aptheker, 1967 (Box 95, Folder 9)
  - Notes, clippings, pamphlets on New Delhi visit, 1967 Nov. (Box 95, Folder 10)
  - Styron & Nat Turner clippings, 1967 - 1972 (Box 95, Folder 11)
  - Clippings & notes, 1967 (Box 95, Folder 12)
  - Clippings on Aptheker assasination attempt, 1967 (Box 95, Folder 13)
  - Clippings, 1967 (Box 95, Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous clippings, 1967 (Box 95, Folder 15)
  - Miscellaneous, 1967 (Box 95, Folder 16)
  - Aptheker, Bettina. Social psychology & the student movement. Ethical Impact, 1967 (Box 95, Folder 17)
  - Abstracts AFL-CIO, 1967 (Box 95, Folder 18)
  - Marxism & religion, 1967 (Box 95, Folder 19)
  - Relevance of Marxism, 1967 (Box 95, Folder 20)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Guerilla-Kriegfuhrung in der Geschichte der Vereinigten Staaten von Amerika. -- In Jahrbuch fur Wirtschaftsgeschichte, 1968 Jan., tms (13 p.) (Box 95, Folder 21)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. On racism and the Civil War, 1968 Jan. 28, tms (5 p.) (Box 95, Folder 22)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. On Du Bois clubs "for Chicago meeting", 1968 Mar. 1 (Box 95, Folder 23)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Marxism, religion, and revolution. -- In Cross Currents. -- Vol. 18, no. 2, 1968 Spring (Box 95, Folder 24)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Marxism and religion. -- In Religion, 1968 Spring, 2 sets of tearsheets (Box 95, Folder 25)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Truth and Nat Turner: an exchange. -- The Nation. -- Vol. 206, 1968 Apr. 22 (Box 95, Folder 26)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. A top scholar documents illegality in Viet war, 1968 Apr. 30 (Box 95, Folder 27)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Ideas in our times: Marxism, religion, and revolution. -- In Political Affairs, 1968 May (Box 95, Folder 28)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Styron's Turner vs. Nat Turner. -- In The New South Student. -- Vol. 5, no. 4, 1968 May (Box 95, Folder 29)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Academic freedom in the United States. -- In The New Republic, 1968 May (Box 95, Folder 30)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. France today and revolution: some lessons., 1968 May 27, tms (3 p.) (Box 95, Folder 31)
    Contains manuscript of article published in The Worker, 1968 June 6.
  - Aptheker, Herbert. New introduction for To be free, 1968 June, tms (2 p.) (Box 95, Folder 32)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Book review: James Boyd's Above the law. -- p. 35-38. -- In Political Affairs, 1968 June (Box 95, Folder 33)
    Includes notes
  - Aptheker, Herbert. On Vietnam: draft for discussions at the World Conference for Peace emergency meeting in Nicosia, Cypress, 1968 June 6 - 8 (Box 95, Folder 34)
    Includes Herbert Aptheker's Ideas in our times: For peace and freedom: the Cypress chapter, tms (13 p.), 1968 June 17, and correspondence between Isabelle Blume and Herbert Aptheker.
  - Aptheker, Herbert. France today and the revolution: some lessons, 1968 June 16 (Box 95, Folder 35)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Review of They took their stand by Emma Geralds Sterne, 1968 July 3, tms (2 p.) (Box 95, Folder 36)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Review of While six million died by Arthur D. Morse, 1968 July 10, tms (3 p.) (Box 95, Folder 37)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Letter to the Editor of Science Magazine re: Tinbergen article "On war and peace in animals and Man", 1968 July 10, tms (3 p.) (Box 95, Folder 38)
    Includes clipping of Tinbergen article
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Review of The Social and political thought of Karl Marx by Shlomo Avineri, 1968 July 19, tms (3 p.) (Box 95, Folder 39)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Review of Herbert Marcuse's Negations: essays in critical theory, 1968 July 22, tms (3 p.) (Box 95, Folder 40)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. History and mythology., 1968 July 25, tms (2 p.) (Box 95, Folder 41)
    Includes clipping of published article in the Daily World, p. 8, 1968 Sept. 11.
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Review of Herbert Marcuse's Negations: essays in critical theory. -- p. 7. -- In Daily World, 1968 July 27, 2 copies (Box 95, Folder 42)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Ideas in our times: Attempting a new history, part II, 1968 July 29, tms (16 p.) (Box 96, Folder 1)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. New historians and new history, parts I & II: [review of Barton J. Bernstein, ed. Towards a new past: dissenting essays in American history], 1968 July 29, tms (30 p.) (Box 96, Folder 2)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Book review of Emma Gelders Sterne's They took their stand. -- p. 7 -- In Daily World, 1968 July 30, 2 copies (Box 96, Folder 3)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Book review of Ernest Becker's The structure of evil: an essay on the unification of the science of Man., 1968 July 31, tms (3 p.) (Box 96, Folder 4)
    Draft of Daily World article. Includes quotes from Becker Book, 2 p.
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Notes on North Carolina meeting, 1968 Aug. (Box 96, Folder 5)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Book review of Shlomo Avineri's The social and political though of Karl Marx. -- p. 7 -- In Daily World, 1968 Aug. 2 (Box 96, Folder 6)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. American 'Democracy', 1968 Aug. 9, tms (4 p.) + tls (Box 96, Folder 7)
    Includes letter from T. Olaru [Scintei, Bucharest].
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Book review of Wellington Long's The new Nazis of Germany, 1968 Aug. 14, tms (3 p.) (Box 96, Folder 8)
    Includes notes from Long's book (2 p.) and one issue of the Democratic German Report. -- Vol. 17, no. 15 (1968 July 24).
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Science diverted from its task: Becker in the steps of Mills: book review of Ernest Becker's The Structure of Evil. -- p. 8 -- In The Daily World, 1968 Aug. 29 (Box 96, Folder 9)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. The Catholic left by James Colaianni: review. -- p. 8 -- In Daily World, 1968 Aug. 31 (Box 96, Folder 10)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Anti-culture, 'freedom', and counter-revolution, 1968 Sept., tms (3 p.) (Box 96, Folder 11)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. On the G.D.R. and the Communist Party, U.S.A., 1968 Sept., tms (4 p.) (Box 96, Folder 12)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. The impending U.S. elections: an analysis. For Problems of Peace & Socialism. -- In World Marxist Review, 1968 Sept. 15, tms (11 p.) (Box 96, Folder 13)
    Includes notes, clippings, and World Marxist Review tearsheets.
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Africa and the Soviet Union, 1968 Sept. 20, tms (3 p.) (Box 96, Folder 14)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Blurred look backward: book review of Staughton Lynd's Intellectual origins of American radicalism, 1968 Sept. 21 - 22, clipping (Box 96, Folder 15)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Ideas in our times: Czechoslovakia and the present epoch, 1968 Oct., tms (15 p.) (Box 96, Folder 16)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Czechoslovakia and the present epoch, part II, [1968], tms (20 p.) (Box 96, Folder 17)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Ideas in our times: Christians and the Marxian vision. -- In Political Affairs, 1968 Oct. (Box 96, Folder 18)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. African nations and the U.S.S.R. -- p. 6 -- In Daily World, 1968 Oct. 5 (Box 96, Folder 19)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Crimes too big for statistics. -- p. 6 -- In Daily World, 1968 Oct. 8, 2 copies (Box 96, Folder 20)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Comment on Earl Ziemke's Stalingrad to Berlin: the German defeat in the East. -- For the Daily World, 1968 Oct. 22, tms (1 p.) (Box 96, Folder 21)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. On civil rights and black power books, 1968 Oct. 24, tms (6 p.) (Box 96, Folder 22)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. U.S. apologia for Hitler. Letter to the Editor. -- In Daily World, 1968 Oct. 29 (Box 96, Folder 23)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. New historians and a new history: review of Barton Bernstein's Toward a new past. -- In The New South Student. -- Vol. 5, no. 5, 1968 Nov. (Box 96, Folder 24)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. On Bernd Hartmann's Events in Czechoslovakia in the light of Marxism., 1968 Nov., tms (3 p.) (Box 96, Folder 25)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Du Bois as historian: notes and carbon [1 of 2], 1968 Nov. 11 (Box 96, Folder 26)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Du Bois as historian: notes and carbon [2 of 2], 1968 Nov. 11 (Box 96, Folder 27)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Review of Libel and academic freedom by Arnold M. Rose. -- In Daily World, 1968 Nov. 12 (Box 96, Folder 28)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Review of Blanstein & Woock, eds. Man against poverty: World War III, 1968 Nov. 15, tms (3 p.) (Box 96, Folder 29)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Review of Paul Eidelberg's The philosophy of the American constitution, 1968 Nov. 26, tms (2 p.) (Box 96, Folder 30)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. DuBridge and DuBarry, 1968 Dec., tms (2 p.) (Box 96, Folder 31)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. New historians and a new history: review of Barton Bernstein's Toward a new past. -- In The New South Student. -- Vol. 5, no. 6, 1968 Dec. (Box 96, Folder 32)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. West German student leader views Czech events. -- p. 4. -- In Daily World, 1968 Dec. 4, 2 copies (Box 96, Folder 33)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Du Bois as historian, 1968 Dec. 4, tms (25 p.) + tls (Box 96, Folder 34)
    Includes letter from Otto H. Olsen
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Book review of Julius Lester's Look out, Whitey! Black power's gon' get your mama! -- For the Daily World, 1968 Dec. 11, tms (2 p.) (Box 96, Folder 35)
    Includes quotes from the Leste book and clippings of the review from the Daily World.
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Ideas in our times: Law and order: lies and hypocrisy, 1968 Dec. 17, tms (8 p.) (Box 96, Folder 36)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Book review of Alfred Blaustein and Robert Zangrando, ed. Civil rights and the American negro. -- For the Daily World, 1968 Dec. 24, tms (2 p.) + an (2 p.) (Box 96, Folder 37)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Lenin's 'Letter to American workers. -- For Pravda, [ca. 1968], tms (4 p.) (Box 96, Folder 38)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Ideas in our times, 1968 (Box 96, Folder 39)
  - Printed articles and letters to the editor by Herbert Aptheker in newspapers and magazines, 1968 (Box 96, Folder 40)
  - Letters to the editor / Herbert Aptheker, 1968 (Box 96, Folder 41)
  - Conference for a new Marxist Daily newspaper: notes for remarks, New York City, 1968 Jan. 28 (Box 96, Folder 42)
  - An interview with Dr. Herbert Aptheker. -- In Confrontation [Brown University]. -- Vol. 1, no. 2, 1968 Feb. (Box 96, Folder 43)
  - Stanford - Santa Clara Ecumenical Colloquium meeting, 1968 Feb. 16 - 17 (Box 96, Folder 44)
    Includes notes (1 p.)
  - Betts, Robert. How reds attack the campus. -- In Waterloo Courier, 1968 Mar. (Box 96, Folder 45)
  - University of Kentucky seminar notes, 1968 Apr. 23 (Box 96, Folder 46)
  - Williams College. The Vietnam war: analysis and alternatives., 1968 May 6 (Box 96, Folder 47)
  - Quo vadis, U.S.A.?: an interview with H. Aptheker. -- In Berliner Leitung, 1968 May 31 (Box 96, Folder 48)
  - Dunham, Barrows. Review of Marxism and Christianity: a symposium. -- In The Worker, 1968 June 23 (Box 96, Folder 49)
  - Liturgical Week, 1968 Aug. (Box 97, Folder 1)
  - International Publishers Book News. To be free: press release, 1968 Oct. (Box 97, Folder 2)
  - 53rd annual meeting of the Association for the Study of Nego Life and History: program, New York City, 1968 Oct. 4 (Box 97, Folder 3)
  - American Historical Association 83rd annual meeting schedule, 1968 Dec. 27 (Box 97, Folder 4)
    Includes description of Herbert Aptheker's presentation Du Bois as a historian.
  - Shaw, Peter. The uses of autobiography. -- p. 136-150. -- In American Scholar, 1968 - 1969 Winter (Box 97, Folder 5)
  - Inde, Horst. Die Black Muslims in den USA. -- In Wissenschaftlichte Zeitschrift der Humboldt-Universitat zu Berlin, 1968 (Box 97, Folder 6)
  - Styron & Nat Turner: Nation articles, 1968 (Box 97, Folder 7)
  - Reviews of Herbert Aptheker, 1968 (Box 97, Folder 8)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Chronology of lectures, 1968 (Box 97, Folder 9)
  - Speaking engagements, 1968 (Box 97, Folder 10)
  - Lecture notes, 1968 (Box 97, Folder 11)
  - Clippings, 1968 (Box 97, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous, 1968 (Box 97, Folder 13)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Review of Civil rights and the American Negro., 1969 Jan. 7 (Box 97, Folder 14)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Ideas in our times: present needs in the study of Afro-American history, 1969 Jan. 17, tms (6 p.) (Box 97, Folder 15)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Review of Understanding Negro history, Dwight Hoover, ed., 1969 Jan. - Feb., tms (2 p.) (Box 97, Folder 16)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Preface for 1969 edition of And why not everyman?: the struggle to end slavery in the United States, 1969 Feb., tms (2 p.) (Box 97, Folder 17)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. The works of Anthony William Amo, African scholar of the 18th Century, 1969 Feb. 4, tms (5 p.) (Box 97, Folder 18)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Ideas in our time: irrationalism and reaction, 1969 Feb. 17, tms (7 p.) (Box 97, Folder 19)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. The Brave free world, 1969 Feb. 21, tms (3 p.) (Box 97, Folder 20)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Anthony William Amo: discovery of a black philosopher. -- In Milwaukee Courier, 1969 Feb. 22 (Box 97, Folder 21)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Racism and anti-semitism: lecture at New York University, 1969 Feb. 27, tms (4 p.) (Box 97, Folder 22)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Ideas in our times: present needs in the study of Afro-American history. -- In Political Affairs. -- Vol. 48, 1969 Feb. (Box 97, Folder 23)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. The brave free world, 1969 Mar. 17, tms (3 p.) (Box 97, Folder 24)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Ideas in our time: anti-semitism and racism: [speech at Town Hall, New York City], 1969 Mar. 19, tms (6 p.) (Box 97, Folder 25)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. The superiority of the Negro. -- In American Dialog. -- Vol. 2, no. 3, 1969 Spring (Box 97, Folder 26)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Book reviews. -- In American Quarterly. -- Vol. 21, no. 1, 1969 Spring (Box 97, Folder 27)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. The Negro college student in the 1920's: years of preparation and protest: an introduction. -- In Science and Society. -- Vol. 33, no. 2, 1969 Spring (Box 97, Folder 28)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Comments on papers delivered ... at 2nd annul Pacific Northwest Labor History Conference, 1969 Apr. 10, tms (5 p.) (Box 97, Folder 29)
    Includes Sally M. Miller's Victor Berger: a progressive era radical and the labor movement, tms (19 p.); Stuart Bruce Kaufman's Samuel Gompers and the radical origins of the American Federation of Labor, tms (26 p.); and notes
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Brave free world, 1969 Apr. 12, 1 p. (Box 97, Folder 30)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Brave free world III: the censor cries censorship, 1969 Apr. 25, tms (4 p.) (Box 97, Folder 31)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. The disarray of the Left - Cause and cure. Technology forum: notes, 1969 Apr. 25 (Box 97, Folder 32)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Remarks on Dorothy Healey, 1969 May (Box 97, Folder 33)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Die U.S.A.: Kranke Fuhrungsmacht des Imperialismus. -- In Einhart, 1969 May (Box 97, Folder 34)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. The 19th convention of the Communist Party of the United States, 1969 May 6, tms (4 p.) (Box 97, Folder 35)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Ideas in our times: The United States: a society in crisis: parts 1 & 2, 1969 May 22, tms (25 p.) + an (Box 97, Folder 36)
    Includes notes for speech on same topic
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Review of C.S. Calian's Berdyaev's philosophy of hope: a contribution to Marxist-Catholic dialogue, 1969 May 31, tms (3 p.) (Box 97, Folder 37)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. The American Institute for Marxist Studies. -- In Internationale Wissenschaftliche Korrespondenz zur Greschicte der deutschen Arbeiterbewegung (W. Berlin). -- No. VIII, 1969 June (Box 97, Folder 38)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Remarks for June 8, 1969, 1969 June, tms (4 p.) (Box 97, Folder 39)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. New developments in U.S. anti-war movement, 1969 June 18, tms (16 p.) (Box 97, Folder 40)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Remarks at the Commission on Mid-East, World Assembly for Peace, Berlin, 1969 June 21, tms (5 p.) (4 copies) (Box 97, Folder 41)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Twenty years of a new Germany, 1969 June 25, tms (2 p.) (Box 97, Folder 42)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Reply to Comrade Lumer, 1969 July 3, tms (2 p.) (Box 98, Folder 1)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. The brave free world: David and Goliath, 1969 July 7, tms (4 p.) + 1 clipping (1 p.) (Box 98, Folder 2)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Speech delivered at National Conference for a United Front against Facism, Oakland [Black Panther Party], 1969 July 18 (Box 98, Folder 3)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Author's query, 1969 July 24, tms (1 p.) (Box 98, Folder 4)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Review of Theodore Draper's The abuse of power, 1969 July 30, tms (3 p.) (Box 98, Folder 5)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Review of The birth of god by James Kavanaugh, 1969 July 31, tms (2 p.) (Box 98, Folder 6)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. America's political crisis, 1969 July, tms (7 p.) (Box 98, Folder 7)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. The United States: decay and rebirth, 1969 Aug. 1, tms (6 p.) + 1 telegram + clippings (Box 98, Folder 8)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Comments on Father Riga's Proposal, 1969 Sept. 19, tms, ams, als (Box 98, Folder 9)
    Includes correspondence from Peter Riga, and Peter J. Riga's Marxist-Christian dialogue: a proposal, tms (19 p.)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Mr. Bourke's The social critics and the end of American innocence: 1907 - 1921: a comment. -- In Journal of American Studies, Univ. of Manchester, 1969 Sept. 25, tms (3 p.) (Box 98, Folder 10)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Imperialism and irrationalism. -- In Telos. -- No. 4, 1969 Fall, tms (3 p.) (Box 98, Folder 11)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. The United States: decay and rebirth. -- International Affairs (Moscow), 1969 Oct. (Box 98, Folder 12)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Marxism and war, 1969 Oct., tms (3 p.) (Box 98, Folder 13)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Brave free world: he faces 98 years for speaking his mind [On Eli de Gortari], 1969 Oct. 18, tms (4 p.) + tls (Box 98, Folder 14)
    Includes letter for Eli de Gortari to Dirk Struik, 1969 Sept. 2, 2 p.
  - Aptheker, Herbert. U.S.A.: time of change. -- In Pravda, 1969 Oct. 30 (Box 98, Folder 15)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Ideas in our times: Krupp: capitalism's Quintessence, 1969 Nov., tms (18 p.) (Box 98, Folder 16)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Review of Theodore Draper's Abuse of power: U.S. foreign policy from Cuba to Vietnam. -- In Labour Monthly, 1969 Nov. (Box 98, Folder 17)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Americans and the GDR. -- In Daily Worker, 1969 Nov. 4 (Box 98, Folder 18)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Parteig der Zuversicht. -- In Horizont, 1969 Nov. 23 (Box 98, Folder 19)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. The brave free world: something horrible did take place, 1969 Nov. 24, tms (3 p.) (Box 98, Folder 20)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Leninism and the United States, 1969 Dec. 8, tms (4 p.) (Box 98, Folder 21)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. The American Civil War. -- In Studien uber die Revolution, 1969 (Box 98, Folder 22)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Czechoslovakia and counter-revolution: why the Socialist countries intervened. -- New York: New Outlook Publishers, 1969 (Box 98, Folder 23)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Die USA: Kranke fuhrungsmacht des imperialismus. -- In Einheit (Berlin). -- No. 5, 1969 (Box 98, Folder 24)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Lenin and racism., [1969], tms (5 p.) + tn (Box 98, Folder 25)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. The Negro college student in the 1920s: years of preparation and protest: an introduction, 1969, tms (21 p.) (Box 98, Folder 26)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Neue Entwicklungen in der Antikriegsbewegung der USA. -- In Einheit. -- No. 8, 1969 (Box 98, Folder 27)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Review of bibliography of Negro history & culture for young readers, 1969, tms (1 p.) (Box 98, Folder 28)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. The system stands accused. -- In The World, [ca. 1969] (Box 98, Folder 29)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. Wen die Gotter verderben wollen ... -- In Jahrbuch f. Wirtschaftsgeschichte. -- Vol. 3, 1969 (Box 98, Folder 30)
  - Aptheker, Herbert. [Russian language article]. -- In International Affairs. -- No. 10, 1969, tms (1 p.) (Box 98, Folder 31)
  - Letters to the Editor, 1969 (Box 98, Folder 32)
  - Reviews of Herbert Aptheker, 1969 (Box 98, Folder 33)
  - Reviews, 1969 (Box 98, Folder 34)
  - Review of Herbert Aptheker's To be free: studies in American Negro history. -- In Kliatt, 1969 Apr. (Box 98, Folder 35)